<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://miere.observer/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://miere.observer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-04-20T20:18:43+10:00</updated><id>https://miere.observer/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Miere’s Personal Observations</title><subtitle>Personal observations made by myself. I write about technology, software engineering, history and, ocasionally, politics. I shall try my best to keep it as scientific as possible, using facts to support my point of view. Hopefully, you will give me a hand whenever I did a mistake.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Producing professional deliverables</title><link href="https://miere.observer/engineering/2020/04/20/Producing-professional-deliverables.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Producing professional deliverables" /><published>2020-04-20T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2020-04-20T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://miere.observer/engineering/2020/04/20/Producing-professional-deliverables</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://miere.observer/engineering/2020/04/20/Producing-professional-deliverables.html">&lt;p&gt;It was 2008 when I first received a bad feedback about a job I did. My team was performing
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/360-degree_feedback&quot;&gt;360 Degree Feedback&lt;/a&gt;. The feedbacks were appaling. I never had that feeling before. Why did people feel like I was a complete fraud? I mean, they complained quite a lot about how they were supposed to maintain such a messy service. One, even asked me if I got any mental problem.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="engineering" /><summary type="html">It was 2008 when I first received a bad feedback about a job I did. My team was performing 360 Degree Feedback. The feedbacks were appaling. I never had that feeling before. Why did people feel like I was a complete fraud? I mean, they complained quite a lot about how they were supposed to maintain such a messy service. One, even asked me if I got any mental problem.</summary></entry></feed>